[Music]
hello you found the portal I'm your host
Eric Weinstein and I'm here today with
author of the pendulum Julie Linda Julie
welcome thank you so Julie we're doing
this in a little bit of a different
situation than I usually do you've been
staying with us here in Los Angeles in
our home for several nights and we did
not know each other beforehand but you
are on a book tour is that right that's
right and I got very lucky staying with
you know we've been having a blast
talking to you and just really enjoying
your stay can you tell us a little bit
about who you are and what book it is
that has brought you from Europe over to
the States
yes well I am a cosmopolitan who ended
up 24 years ago settling in Sweden had
the pleasure and surprise of ending up
living on a small isolated island in
Sweden for about a decade where I had
some time to start to reflect about my
family's past and also gruesome roots to
start to to be able to become grounded
in order to be able to do the work I
didn't know I was going to do the work
but then in April 2010 went to the
Buddhist archive in Germany and asked
whether they had any material on my
grandparents who were German I was born
in Brazil in 1967 my mother was born in
occupied Poland in 1941 and most people
around me always laughed a bit that I
hadn't put two and two together but I
guess I had tried to look away from
those facts and so the documents I
received there set me off on a very long
journey I didn't know that it would be
that long six year journey through
Germany Poland Brazil and Paraguay to
learn about
the role my grandparents played in the
Third Reich wow that's a hell of an
answer to a question oh here you are
talking about
I guess secrets deeply hidden from you
about why a German girl would be growing
up in Brazil can you tell us a little
bit about your evolution as to how you
came to understand that there might be
something fairly interesting in this
family story well first of all there's a
part of me that's Germans my mother's
German but my father was an American
which also made matters more interesting
because I also had an I guess an
outsider's perspective as well as an
insider's perspective into my German
heritage the way it started is hard to
say but the way I usually think of it is
back in a time when I was a two-year-old
and put into a German dirndl so a
traditional German dress whenever my
German grandparents came to visit from
the interior because they were settled
on an estate near the Brazilian
Paraguayan border and I noticed from the
albums that I always had one of these
traditional dresses on when they came to
visit which to me seemed very strange
given that I was the daughter of an
American and a German and I was living
in Brazil there are large German
communities there so maybe you could
argue it that way but it was a little
strange and in that girl's eyes I can
see and I also remember growing up
burying a very considerable shame and
the nature of shame is different than
guilt when you are guilt when you feel
guilty you know what you've done it's a
reaction to something you think you've
done wrong but shame is something else
it's a feeling of self self
worthlessness
and you don't necessarily know why it's
there so I bore this with me from a very
early age probably because my mother was
very frustrated about her past and
didn't really know how to deal with it I
think she wanted to love her parents
like all children want to love their
parents yet at the same time understood
that they had this troublesome past that
was simply not acceptable in the new era
that she was living in and so therefore
I I had this with me then I got educated
but I had a very close relationship with
my grandmother whose affection I guess I
sought because I didn't have a close
relationship with my mother and my
grandmother remained a devoted Nazi to
the end of her life I just didn't know I
hadn't I hadn't realized that she wasn't
well so your grandma was a was a Nazi to
the end of a really 100 and 300 years
old so she died in what year she died in
2014 she was born the year the Titanic
sunk oh wow so it's pretty amazing to
think about it - Part C 2014 well
obviously she wasn't a Nazi until until
the 1930s right no no of course but one
sense is from a little bit that you've
said that the commitment was made and
there was somehow no digging out of it
and so it was just kept going full speed
ahead no I think you can can compare it
to the commitment of some people today
to alternative facts at some point
you've just gone too far and you can't
back out but it does leave it's
devastation
you know she was not free of nightmares
and depression and and so forth after
the war but anyway she and I became
quite close or so I thought she was a
well-read person she loved classical
music she loved nature we spent lots of
time together
even more time when I got a Fulbright in
Germany
let's humanize her a little bit yeah
what kind of classical music did you
love well she loved she loved the
classical German composers particularly
from from the north of Germany she also
loved Handel she listened to a lot
piano music German piano music I'm
trying to think if it's not coming to me
right away now all of them that she
liked but you know she listened to
Beethoven and Bach and Mozart and all of
those so very clearly culturally high
German culture absolutely and high
German literature she passed on a number
of the books that were her favorites to
me and a lot of it you know well-known
high german literature so when she then
started tossing out shards of this old
ideology during our meetings in her
apartment in southern Germany where we
were having a cup of tea or a cup of
coffee and a piece of cake
I was always stunned and shocked
and didn't know what to do with it
except to get up and go do the dishes
and over time though doing that gets to
you because you end up in the position
of the bystander you end up feeling
rotten inside when you don't stand up
and say but that's wrong that's not true
and this was particularly so when she
tried to convince me that the Holocaust
was a plot by the international media to
keep Germans down so after the war and I
was at that time studying international
affairs later on I went on to study
german polish relations in the 20th
century at oxford university so i knew
what she was telling me was of course
completely wrong
and yet I didn't say anything to her
because I was so frightened of losing
her affection that's really interesting
conundrum that we can all worry about
but you've really been been through this
where you're you realize that your
deepest emotional and loyalty your
loyalty connections are running to
people who are a mixture of pure evil
and pure normal and goodness I mean you
know an educated family from from
everything I can discern a family where
there was love and caring and then
there's just this horrible festering I
don't know what even to call it I mean
it's just some stain that can't be
removed yeah absolutely and which is why
when I go out to schools and talk about
this I take out an image which is
painted by an artist in Michigan called
Kimo and it's a face that has many
different surfaces and dimensions and
you can't really figure out where
exactly the face is at some level but
the point is that there are many
different facades and that's what I
learned
speaking with my grandmother and when I
when I think about her today but our
conversations as time went by ended up
troubling me a lot and particularly my
own reactions troubled me I was also
troubled by the fact that I was was
influenced by her perspective of Jewish
people because you know she kind of
imparted in various ways that Jewish
people were dangerous to us which was
kind of a reaction of her generation
because they were being punished for
what they did in the Holocaust but I
didn't know that at that time of course
and I did a number of kind of crazy
things to try to counteract that
inheritance of mine to really dig
deep into myself and blow the whistle
and say hey that is a totally insane
idea Jewish people are not dangerous to
you we you have been taking your life in
your own hands staying with us night
after night Julie I don't feel that way
at all I feel very well taken care of so
do you think your mom knew a great deal
of this history that you somehow were
screened out of or do you think she was
also in the dark about it or is even the
idea of how much we know about our
histories is that word too sharp and
that there's some need for a kind of
layered concept of knowing where you
sort of know something but maybe you
don't know you don't keep a copy of it
that's too crisp in your mind because
it's too dangerous to have it in that
state what's the right question I should
be asking I think there may be we start
with the facts do you think she had a
lot of facts that you didn't have no she
didn't I know that she didn't and
neither did her siblings and neither did
their mother because my grandfather went
to war in the autumn of 1939 and first
of all not all of that is documented
what those men did in Poland secondly a
lot of the documents were destroyed
thirdly they haven't seen any documents
I'm I'm the one who has bothered to go
and find the documents and read them and
there were a lot of them and so I
probably know more than any family
member because I've read primary
documents specifically about what my
grandfather was doing and also just what
people around him were doing in the
areas where he was can you name your
grandfather so that we have a an
individual I just call him oppa I don't
name his name because the people are
there are people who are alive who bear
his last name and I I don't don't want
to make their lives difficult yeah oppa
for the purposes of this podcast yeah
yes and as to these layers I think
you're you're right very right there in
my experience for the sake of the family
unit you look away from certain very
glaring facts I did that I think my
mother and her siblings did that the
family has been our most important unit
of survival since forever and so that's
probably a natural knee-jerk type of
thing to do I think my or I know that my
family knew that my grandfather was in
the SS because later on I met an uncle
so he was the oldest of the siblings I
met him in Paraguay so he oppa
not only volunteered in 1939 but went
straight for the SS he was he joined the
SS back in 1934 already oh wow so he
joined the mounted SS I think what you
should remember is that the SS and 34
was a political primarily political
organization and the waffen-ss of the
military wing of the SS emerged out of
this as the 30s went on but he joined as
one of Hitler's political soldiers and
specifically the mounted SS in 1934
mainly because well the mounted SS was
very prestigious the organization was
also the mounted SS was created out of
writing associations that were drafted
into the organization so you some people
argue that they didn't have a choice but
it's more complicated than that but so
he he was pumped full of propaganda
throughout the 1930s because he was a
member of the SS throughout so that by
the time he got into Poland he was
really quite full of it
and you know Hitler and Himmler and the
other Nazi leaders didn't really give
very precise instructions to the SS when
they went into Poland because they
trusted that they'd pump these people so
full of propaganda that if they just
Unleashed them they would fight a very
brutal racial war which is exactly what
they did and with no documents
indicating that they had been instructed
to do so yeah so that in part and I
think this is a lot of relevance for
today so let's just go there one way of
making sure that your fingerprints
aren't on something is to pump people
fill full pump people full of ideology
and then we know enough about how
ideology sits in the human mind to know
what's likely to happen next I mean
there's you know this famous example
from history of the king saying well no
one rid me of this troublesome priest he
doesn't have to give an order to execute
he just has to say this idly to himself
and then he knows what happens and then
there is no record so in effect there is
no trigger pulling finger from the
central command no and this is also
reflected in the way my grandfather and
others others who had a similar role as
he had as the war went on in occupied
Poland is reflected in the way they
behaved because he became engaged in a
mission set by the Ministry of
Agriculture
so the under the Third Reich to
transform west central Poland to the
breadbasket of the Third Reich because
he was a strained state manager he knew
something about agriculture and that can
sound benign what it in fact means is
deporting or murdering the existing
landowners enslaving the local laborers
and murdering anyone who's slightly
troublesome
and torturing people on a more or less
daily basis early on in the war Himmler
passed a law which established that
these estate managers were the law in
their estates there was no higher law
over them and it's exactly what you were
saying it's a law that says I don't need
to know do do what you have to do
let's terrify yes okay so here you are a
young woman who has grown up in this
unusual developmental environment you're
you went to college with my wife you
guys knew each other perhaps vaguely and
you're living this very modern American
existence at that time how how is this
playing out I mean America you know
American father you're in an American
College you're somehow also the
granddaughter of an SS member who has
you have an inkling at this point that
your grandfather has done unspeakable
things in Poland or not not so much at
Wellesley I didn't think about it so
much although I was very affected by it
because these types of secrets when
they're when they're this heavy yeah
kind of inhabit a family at a cellular
level I mean it is physiological yeah
absolutely okay yes spiritual yeah I
mean I was very sick when I was at
Wellesley
I didn't eat most of the time and so
that was the way it expressed itself
there in fact Pia and I worked out that
we didn't see each other that much
probably because I was hiding out a lot
from people because I I I had pretty
serious eating disorders but these were
all connected to a feeling of low
self-worth that were connected to the
shame that I went around with so I knew
that there was something wrong my
relationship with my mother was
extremely troubled and as the years went
by our family relationships in fact all
of them became quite troubled because
when you have something like this in the
family that the adults knew something
about they didn't know the whole story
but they knew enough and that they try
to keep from themselves it's not so much
they're keeping it from the next
generation they're trying to keep it
away from themselves because they don't
want to think about it then it starts to
strangle their relationships and that
was already going on at that time and
that affected me at a cellular level and
so when I returned to Europe remember I
only spent three years going to college
in the u.s. that was my American
experience okay then I returned to
Europe to do a Fulbright and then went
to Oxford and of course then I went back
into the European realm yeah and of
course got closer and closer and closer
to this and I wasn't that surprised or
today I'm not surprised in retrospect
that my mother was a bit so-so about my
learning German because learning the
German language was a path into this
history without it I would not have been
able to do this could have gone through
the archives No
so I kept getting closer and closer and
closer to this history all the time
without really knowing that I was doing
it but I think there was something in me
that was so desperate about what was
happening in my family because I love my
family it's not because I don't love my
family that I've done this work which is
what some family members may think it's
because I do love my family
and I realized that there needs to be a
little little bit of pain in order to in
order to try to allow some sort of
healing to occur well Julie you were at
Oxford after college in the States and I
think you've picked up some British
understatement when you say that they do
a little bit of pain it sounds like I
hacked a whole lot more than that well I
mean I'm happy to sort of glance at it
using our peripheral vision but we're
talking about an unbelievable burden yes
it's an unbelievable burden but you know
that well let's put it this way there
were it was interesting to me that when
I decided to actively start to pursue
this work in April 2010 as I was moving
towards the decision to go towards the
archives and really exercise my academic
training there were quite a number of
people around me who knew what I was
about to do who said to me that's not
necessary why do you have to do that
that's passed let it be passed it's over
you know they were frightened and some
of them really were extremely animated
when they tried to convince me not to do
this these are well-meaning people who
want the best for me and but what I knew
all the time was that no that is just
going to prolong the suffering not only
for me but for other people for my
children my children were a very big
motivator so do you think that the
people who are trying to dissuade you
were just waiting you because they knew
what you were going to find or was it
because they didn't know what you were
gonna find some people I think most
people thought I would find something
because they knew me too well
knew how troubled I had been they knew
these different pieces of my background
it was as though they already knew and
just wanted to put on the brakes because
they didn't want me to go into that pain
that you surename which is a caring
response at the same time I also think
that there is a selfish dimension to it
because there is this idea in our
society that looking back and looking
particularly looking back at what our
ancestors did and those before us did is
a dangerous thing it's in the myths and
legends of Western culture right and so
I think there was a little element in
that of trying to spare themselves as
well which I sensed and it annoyed me
greatly at the same time I tried to keep
in my mind that these are people who
care about me there was one person in
particular who was a an elderly
professor of German literature a scholar
of Moses Mendelssohn a very great Jewish
scholar who I knew from Wellesley and I
went to see her just before I went to
the archives she lived in a wolfenbüttel
a town not too far from Berlin and she
was 92 at the time and could barely walk
yet she came with me to the train
station and stood there and stared at me
and she had she had survived the
Holocaust because her father had sent
her away to Britain in the late 30s and
she stood there and looked at me and
said please don't do this because she
knew my family very well and realized
that I would find something all right I
got asked what did you find and and when
did you start finding specifics that
really caused cause the story to advance
and friend caused you to change yeah
well the first find was at the German
federal archives
was about a hundred pages which included
mostly information about my grandparents
it was my grandparents application to
marry as an SS couple which required
them to demonstrate their racial
suitability so they went through medical
examinations and there were photographs
of them from all angles and there you
know life accounts written by themselves
but there was also you know information
about all the places where my
grandfather had been stationed in
occupied Poland so so from there I went
to a number of archives found as
denazification papers which
denazification was a process that all
people who joined the party had to go
through after the war and you know
declare what they had been up to and of
course most of them regarded as a joke
anyway eventually I ended up in Poland
at the Institute of national remembrance
in Poznan where they handed me a wad of
documents that were eyewitnesses of
people who had experienced what my
grandfather and his comrades had done in
in local areas and these were
eyewitnesses recorded in 1946 so they
were fairly fresh accounts fresh in
people's minds and there I saw the
accounts of the brutality and of the
beatings and the way the way that he
behaved and how bad I mean I should say
just so you know something about how I
react I can't in general go to holocaust
films yeah it's not a topic that I can
even almost talk about it's too hard but
I'm asking you because this is a journey
that you've been on where I think that
the level of pain and the level of
bravery and the uncertainty
and the complex is what animates the
story and so I'm willing to risk it what
do you find well probably what made me
just sit there and stop and look
completely paralyzed when I sat in the
Institute of national remembrance was
was um you know the the information
about beating of Labor's to to to now
I'm thinking of a Swedish word to to
unconsciousness on a regular basis then
in those documents I did not find
evidence of murder but there were other
documents I found later on that pointed
to that because he would not have tried
to leave for Brazil later on
had he not murdered anyone because in
order to be put on trial you had to have
murdered somebody and these would have
been the local landowner so I did find
some evidence of that but still indirect
you're spared any kind of direct account
of it oh no I would wasn't spirit in its
period a direct account there were
direct accounts of beating people to
total unconsciousness no but I did find
evidence later on of of engagement in a
really awful episode where a small
number of these estate owners would
drive to drive the existing landowners
to a nearby forest tell them to run
towards a trench that they dug
themselves and shoot them well so that's
what I I learned about later on as well
and so there was evidence of that which
wasn't confirmed but it was it was there
on paper and and really that's what
would have got him to to leave so
quickly
to me it would seem very unlikely that
he that wasn't true at all so so anyway
there were some names of people in those
documents of the the people who had
given testimony were named in those
documents from the Polish National
Archive so I set out to try to find see
if I could find some of those families
not expecting to find anyone because we
all know that after that the Soviet
Union came in and redistributed
everybody and so I really didn't expect
to find any of these families in these
places but to my great surprise with the
help of a wonderful young Polish
archivist and historian who could see
how distraught I was and just simply
decided to join me found five families
over different visits to Poland and
those meetings were very important they
were very important to me I don't know
how important they were to those people
but to me they were important and my my
friend who drove with me who's a young
pole whose family had also suffered in
the Second World War
said trust me this is important to them
so I would say that for me those
meetings showed me why I was doing this
work because what I realized in
retrospect I was doing was looking for a
transformational dynamic which is the
portal which is how do we take
everything that we know about the
horrible things human beings have done
to one another and their own experiences
of that perhaps and transform it into a
force that's powerful enough for us to
take another path and those meetings
provided one answer there's lots of
answers do you think it gave any relief
to those people that you were meeting
with do you think there was a double
portal just to riff off you riffing and
I can't answer the question
all I can explain to you is a few of the
reactions and then you can decide
yourself
so the first meeting was with a person
who didn't want to shake my hand because
his memories of what my my grandfather
was name was recognized instantly by all
these people by the way no one had to
remind them of who he was which is a
chilling phrase yeah which is incredible
whatever it is over seven decades later
right
so so he didn't want to shake my hand
and he was very sick he was dying this
man and but he was conscious and able to
register who I was and my friend the
archivist said I don't think there's
much point in carrying on with this
conversation because he doesn't want you
know he experienced you imagine but what
was in my mind was I I must shake this
man's hand I need to show some form of
compassion I can't ask for forgiveness
because I didn't commit the crime but I
want to show humanity and compassion and
I did eventually take his hand and shake
it and he looked completely bewildered
he didn't think that someone like me was
capable I think of shaking his hand and
showing compassion the next person I
went to see was a person who had
dementia and was in his 90s so he
couldn't remember what happened
yesterday but he remembered things that
happened over 70 years ago and his
great-granddaughter was there and
started shouting my grandfather's name
into his ear at which his reaction was
to go back to an episode in time in
which he was hiding in a barn because
some people were being shocked and there
was violence going on outside I I don't
know exactly what the details of it were
but you could see he was recognizing
moment in time and so I begged everyone
present to turn switch this off I didn't
want this to go on and I decided that my
journey was just too selfish journey it
was just for me you know to somehow take
care of my shame and all that and so I
said to my friend the the archivist we
must stop now this is enough because
this is just bringing back bad memories
for people and he said no believe me we
have to go on so there was a third guy
we we met who was what healthy a healthy
85 year old yeah who had a very nice
garden as it happened his father was
most likely my grandfather's gardener on
this estate where he his parents had
worked and he'd been beaten over the
head when he was a 10 year old and my
grandfather had passed him and he'd
forgotten to doff his hat so he had a
scar over his right eye well waste like
it he was beaten directly by your
grandfather so that this your
grandfather's mark it was still visible
on his on his head yes they defy yeah
and when I when I realized this I sat
there and I listened to him for several
hours and I felt awful and but I didn't
really very much to say of course what
should I say I was there to listen and
there was a feeling welling up in me of
wanting to beg for forgiveness because
that was really all I felt I could offer
but he realized that without my saying
very much he was a smart very
intelligent person emotionally
intelligent person and he stood up and
took my lower arms and shook me up and
said this wasn't your fault you didn't
do anything so I want you to go out and
into my garden and I want you to enjoy
my garden and furthermore I want you to
enjoy your life
and then I went out there it stood there
and he and his wife and his daughter was
also around his grown daughter and and
they had been very kind to me served me
cherries picked from their cherry trees
in his garden and anyway I went outside
and stood there and did exactly as he
told me to do and he and his wife came
and stood next to me and it was almost
like we were holding hands we were
touching our hands together and they
were we were just silent together and
later on I thought well of course it
happened right there this
transformational dynamic happened right
there it transformed everything that he
knew and that I knew about our violent
past and what we had experienced into
something else and what he what it was
it for me was that shame became energy
it became responsibility it became a
feeling that you need and have to do
something with this get moving and
without him and without that I wouldn't
have been able to carry on really no I
would have given up because it would
just have been miserable and horrible
and terrible well the thing is it's so
disruptive because I think there's so
many different layers going on in the in
a story like this that most people have
never been called upon to have to pull
to pull apart so many different layers
of meaning importance guilt
responsibility shame the the subtle
shadings that make make us need so many
different words we probably don't even
have all the words that we need and the
idea that for example two people could
have been harmed let's say by the same
person and the person who has harmed
more might be much more capable of
showing compassion empathy mercy to a
descendant of the person
harm them then the person who been
harmed less might have been less capable
so that you know it really isn't just
about what happened but it's also about
how strong people have become how
they're weak how how things played with
their psychology and you know that the
sadness that I have in listening to this
is I don't know how many people in our
modern consumer day and age have been
pushed through this this many layers of
metacognition and self introspection
that I don't know when you give a book
reading how much variation do you think
is in the audience in terms of people
who sort of can deeply relate to stories
like these and people from the sounds
almost like too fantastical to be true
do you find that you find that these
stories consistently find enough depth
in those who read and hear them to fully
appreciate them or do you think that in
part you need to be close to a story
that's profound to have to be forced
into this this level of self understand
hmm that's a very very good question um
on one hand I think that people who come
to events to listen to me by their own
free choice there are events were at
schools and things where they have to
attend they don't have a choice but the
ones where they have a choice and they
register to attend so most people have
of course something there's something in
them that attracts them to this and that
that there's some level of reflection
that has taken place that is bringing
them there something in their personal
histories usually at the same time I'm
always surprised that after I give these
talks often people come up to me to
express their thanks for the work that
I've done but then they'll add something
to that that demonstrates to me that the
there's no way they could really
understand the the very complex dynamics
of what I what I have encountered
because people then fall back on terms
like you know forgiveness and guilts and
things like that which to me are there's
there's a whole there's a whole
vocabulary that's been developed around
this history and the descendants of this
history whether whether they're the
descendants of the victims or the
descendants of the perpetrators or the
descendants of the bystanders there's a
whole vocabulary and to me it's just old
stuff that we fall back on because we're
not prepared to go deeper we're not
prepared to to let ourselves in to other
levels other experiences and so when
people start to talk to me about
forgiveness I try to say to them yes
well I've already explained to you that
I was seeking forgiveness but it was a
rat wheel it didn't lead anywhere didn't
lead forward and it didn't lead forward
because for for me to ask my
grandparents victims for forgiveness is
is it's not doesn't lead us anywhere
doesn't lead me anywhere which is what I
had to learn from one of his victims and
and so but people fall back on this and
other other aspects of vocabulary that
are that we formed around this the
legacy of this history to kind of
protect ourselves from the pain of it
somehow I think that's my read on it
because when you get into the into the
into the pain of it and really get your
hands dirty you start to come up with
other things well you know I have to
tell you that one of the things that's
been very weird about this you
is I've used the opportunity of your
visit with us to explore how many
different dimensions of reaction I
myself am having and you know you and I
have been talking about this a little
bit so I don't mind trying to talk about
it but just it's fascinating to become
metacognitive and look at your own kind
of automated reactions to a story like
this on the one hand I'm just really
impressed by the work that you're doing
with this book and telling this tale and
I think it's it's really important and
we'll come back to this to tell these
stories right at the end of living
memory of the actual Holocaust so it
looks hugely impressed second of all
just to modern people hanging out having
a great conversation it's been great
talking to you third maybe I have this
attitude of I can't believe I'm stuck
with the granddaughter of an SS myapp do
you understand which is like this
lineage to lineage level which is that
you know it's not just me and you it's
like the Jewish people and and their
murderers you know are in under the same
roof
and then you know there's like this
selfish thing which is this is really
important for for I think for us Jews to
do some hard work which is Germany was
one of the most impressive cultures
anywhere in terms of its intellectual
artistic contributions and I am all
wrapped up in the incredible
contribution to world history that is
German and my belief is that it is not
safe to have a very guilty Germany
perhaps as we saw with the refugee
crisis where you're making sort of
almost performative decisions to assuage
guilt that it's the wrong tool to it to
attack the problem on the other hand you
don't want a super triumphalist Germany
to emerge and say none of this was real
and the Germans have been kicked to the
curb so you're trying to figure out
in my opinion should the Jewish people
use the end of living memory of the
Holocaust to finally extend extend a
warmer hand up to Germany not that
Germany is suffering economically I mean
but Germany was also just the seat of
unbelievable genius at a level that
we've scarcely seen in the world I mean
you have the Italian Renaissance but
there was a period of German
contribution which was unparalleled and
I think that we have to do this really
hard work that I'm sort of not prepared
to do and we talked about a very weird
metaphor now I wonder if we can draw you
in we were talking about how people get
angry that the the untrue story gets
disturbed when you do this kind of
research and I went into our one of our
smartphones and I found this triptych of
three images originally of something I
think was a fresco or a painting that
had been beautiful that it in the second
panel that had gotten damaged but in the
third panel there was a terrible
restoration of the damaged painting and
it was almost cartoon like and I worry
that what we're left with right at the
moment is a bit of a cartoon and what
you're really trying to say is I want to
go back before this bad restoration and
you're in the case of your family's
history let's say and look at both the
beauty and the damage that was your
family more honestly in the hopes of
maybe a better restoration can you talk
about sort of I know that you're in a
strange place with your mom can you talk
about kind of the love that you feel for
your family and your mom having done
this work and having me tell you that I
you know I'm just being open that I'm
struggling with the fact that you're in
my home
and I think that you know this is just
this is really courageous work to be
doing can you talk about what you're
trying to do for your family first of
all I wanted to say that you are having
me in my home and having this
conversation is the work so you are
doing the work so you don't have to say
that you are not doing the work you are
doing the work right now and as far as
my as that image goes that you shared
with me of this poor restoration I
reacted to that immediately as a the
best representation of what has happened
in my family that I have seen so far
really visually I think you grasped it
so fast and which means that we're
getting somewhere with our conversation
but but if I think of you ask me about
the love of my family and if I had not
done this work I can safely say that I
would have hated several members of my
family I don't want to say which ones
it's you don't have to know I really
would have hated them not just the
generation that committed the crimes but
the generation afterwards too I would
have hated them for lying to me about
very serious things and leaving me with
a shame that I felt at a cellular level
not only me but my sister too and she's
younger than I am so my job was to
protect her and I couldn't I couldn't
protect her from this messed up her life
for a long time
but going back and for example getting
in a Jeep with a Brazilian genealogist
in Brazil and driving out into the
interior of Brazil where my mother and
her some of her siblings ended up
because my grandma thought parents went
there because of what they'd done in
Europe and seeing what a young teenager
faced a life in a wilderness a dangerous
wilderness a place dominated by the drug
trade
having your youth taken away from you
not being able to grow up in Germany
which after all as you said had a very
rich and old culture having your just
having your opportunities taken like
that and as I stood actually on this
estate was the this place where they had
established themselves and their
interiors on looked at the structures
that were still standing there the man
who's with me said so I take a picture
of you in front of this and I said I
never want to have a picture of me in
front of this ever this is the source of
our suffering this is the source of my
mother suffering and I realized then how
much sympathy I had for her situation
well and for her siblings as well I
don't think they really realized that
that's part of the consequence of this
work today I have a sympathy for them
and it's not like feeling sorry for just
a you know like a hurt person it's it
it's a it's a deep love of of them as
you would love a person who you can see
is enduring the unbearable you know we
all have children you have a you have
children who are teenagers I have
children who are just over the teenage
years and if you just think of them in
that situation their future just taken
from them pulled out from under their
feet
by parents who had committed crimes it's
a terrible thing and so for me I there
is a healing in that awful moment
because otherwise I would have remained
in a in the space of of hatred which is
exactly where we need to not be which is
exactly that what everyone needs to get
out of wherever they can yeah I mean I'm
I'm finding our current vogue for
talking about oppression very bizarre
because it to me
much of it lacks the I don't know what
to call it the texture of really deep
discussions about how do these crimes
perpetuate themselves and propagate
really is a wave in the in the medium of
our generational structure inside of our
families that you see something that
goes wrong and then it cascades
generation after generation you know in
my own case that one of the things I
wrestle with is that my family I think
for the best of reasons became
interested in far left politics and that
blinded them to the horrors of communism
and Stalinism for a period of time when
the US was you know not fully aware of
what exactly had been going on in the
Soviet Union it was possible to think
that that maybe the Soviet Union was
trying to build a better world they were
more open to you know blacks migrating
them to Moscow or you know interracial
marriages or whatever that that were
less comfortable in the u.s. who knows
and from that you know a blind eye is
turned because we don't know how to die
in ala carte politically it's very hard
to say well these aspects were positive
these aspects were negative and we keep
finding very simplistic solutions that
work their way through the you know the
world historical spirit
but you know tens of millions of people
can die at a time as dumb ideas are
explored what work do you think we
should be doing now like what do you
think the most important thing is for
people who can make the leap to
metacognition and kind of look in on
themselves and say isn't it interesting
that I'm simultaneously feeling you know
like the both the blessings of
multiculturalism and the need to have
cultures that are exclusive in order
that there are cultures that can be made
into multi cultures so you know that
that's a great contradiction right there
that culturalism is based on exclusion
multiculturalism is based on inclusion
we can't resolve it what is our work
right now do you think for 1919 this
time yeah well I don't want to go into
this typical diatribe about we have to
reduce polarization and all that you
know simoleons
yeah because in some ways the
polarization induces a lot of thinking
and reactions and forces new things to
emerge and forces people to look for a
new way new ways in a new way out of
this situation well I can only refer to
what I've been doing
I can't tell other people what they
should be doing and so what is a person
who has been done this kind of work do
yes well you're living in Sweden yeah so
that's your base of opera yeah yeah I
live in Sweden and and although I I come
to the United States and and I write in
English so so therefore I speak here
really I've been involved in doing the
work in Sweden and the direction that's
taken me is that I have become engaged
in
different circles of individuals who
have very different areas of expertise
but are working at a very high level of
their field but have decided that it is
insufficient that they remain in their
fields we will not find a way forward
that way we have to come together in
different networks with our different
areas of expertise and address problems
that come up so when I was pulled in by
a bunch of IT experts who are fighting
white supremacy on the internet I don't
like to use the word fighting let's say
counteracting ok white supremacism on
the internet and asked to participate in
some of their projects
I was wondered what it was I could do
because I don't know anything about what
they do but as it happened they saw that
there were things I was doing they
couldn't do and so one of the
manifestations of this collaboration is
that we were called upon to help an area
of Sweden that was being lamed by white
supremist white supremacy so there was a
neo-nazi party that had brought a town
to a halt and as it turned out the
solution was not to try to get at the
neo-nazis the solution was to move into
that society and to inspire it to
mobilize itself and also to bring in all
the major stakeholders business the
church local government whatever
everyone who played a role there and to
get them to decide that their community
was too important to allow the the
things that bound them together
originally which had had weakened to
just fall apart and I think this is a
story
is happening in many parts of the
Western world it's why we see this
situation that we're in that at a
community level there isn't the the the
the things that bind us together I don't
know what we're going to call them that
the bonds okay
have weakened they have weakened in
quality in fact they're becoming so weak
that groups like the neo-nazis and yeah
in other places other groups can just
move in and finish them off so basically
finish off these bonds between us and
just slice right through them and so by
going into this community and saying
come on everyone let's all sit down in
this church which was usually the
largest gathering place in a Swedish
town well not because people are
particularly religious but because
that's where people gather and talk
about how we can strengthen the bonds
between us
within one year people stopped moving
out of that town and business had double
down on its investment in that town
right and to me I guess what I'm what I
should extract from that as a sort of
general thought about what we should be
doing it's seeking just to strengthen
the bonds between us in whatever way we
can which is in my view what you and I
are doing despite the fact that we have
to get over a number of emotional
hurdles I mean to do that but we're
doing it yeah and this is what needs to
happen everywhere where it can
especially among individuals who have
quite a lot of hurdles to jump in order
to you know who were there are a lot of
a lot of emotional difficult emotional
feelings that you need to overcome in
order to strengthen that bond
this has has also been true for me in my
interactions with the Islamic community
I've been approached by people from the
Islamic community who know that there
has to be Holocaust education in their
communities but who also know that their
communities will not welcome hearing it
from a Jewish person or you know a
descendant of a Holocaust survivor which
is terrible it's not always the case but
it is the case sometimes because there
are lots of descendants of Holocaust
survivors who generously give their time
to go around speaking about what
happened to their parents and
grandparents in the Holocaust but often
at least what I have encountered in
Sweden is that in in a number of Islamic
communities it's they just can't they
can't emotionally break through they
can't get over the hurdles they can't
sit down you know even in the u.s.
there's this very bizarre thing that
we're going through where suddenly
slavery which was one kind of a disaster
that you know obviously was bound up in
the founding of the United States has a
tremendous salience inside of the media
commentariat you have a more recent
situation like the Holocaust which you
know is not a North American phenomenon
was a European one but it's much more
recent and the you know the body count
is spectacular and the in the mechanized
horror and deliberate nature of the
whole thing etc etc is fairly
unparalleled and it doesn't have the
same kind of salience because it's
somehow bound up in this question of are
we really talking about oppression or
are we really talking about financial
distribution and redistribution because
the Jewish community is always
vulnerable in a violent way but it's
often very successful in a financial way
and so I've had this theory that you can
tell who's really focused on envy and
has really focused on oppression by how
do they treat whatever the minority
communities are that are very
financially successful in some sphere so
like overseas Chinese or you have Indian
communities in East Africa that are
vulnerable but are often doing well and
the Jewish community is often you know
if you're measuring oppression
financially but you're you're talking
about it as if what you're really upset
about is you know murder or one human
owning another human these things get
pulled apart based on the on which
community you're discussing so for
whatever reason slavery is very central
to the current American discussion and
the vulnerability of Jews is
increasingly invisible to the far left
and the far right and I don't know what
to do about that it just it's too weird
because this I mean in human terms this
is super recent you know there isn't
anyone who can remember slavery and
thank God it's moving into the past so
we have to you know rely on records but
we still have people walking around who
are quite old now who were you know in
the camps or exposed to what was going
on and you know most of those people
were children now if they have any
contact with that at all
but it feels to me like we're we're
unable to remember the horror and the
vulnerability because somehow we just
feel like it doesn't matter anymore I
don't I don't know if you have this
feeling well the thing is that you and I
can't remember the Holocaust because we
didn't live through it no we're both in
our sort of early mid 50s so so that's
gone but what we remember and I think we
remember it intellectually
I don't know if we won't you want to
call it emotionally or spiritually and
we recall it in ourselves what we recall
is the legacy and the reactions of our
families to the Holocaust that's what we
remember and in some of us it's more
acute than in other people and then
those of us were the memory of the
legacy is more acute as in my case for
example I think those people have a very
strong responsibility to support
remembering the legacy of that time
remembering is gone or will be gone soon
well because it's not entirely gone I
shouldn't say that because there are
Holocaust survivors out there doing the
work and continuing to do it but I also
know I Holocaust survivors have been and
their descendants have been like the
greatest supporters of my work they are
the ones who have stood up and said
carry on when I just didn't feel like
you know I could do well there's a
selfish aspect of but you know there's
also this very weird
you know I don't swear that much on
these programs but I will swear a little
bit for emphasis there is just this
incredibly beautiful fuck you to Nazism
when you invite somebody from that
lineage as a Jew into your home and you
say boy did you guys get us wrong you
guys were just such dicks you know it
doesn't it's meant not to do it justice
because there's nothing you can say to
the Holocaust but like all of these
things that I'm reading on the internet
about how Jews control everything and
the narrative and you know spend time
with Jews I don't know anybody who's
being invited as elders of zion to
examine its protocols it's just it's a
very bizarre thing that when people
become divorced from Jews and Judaism
they start telling incredible stories
inside of their mind as to what it must
be and what it represents so I mean I
think that there's a way in which we
need you to tell the story I think that
there's a way in which we test our own
strength
do what Emma you know because this is a
struggle for you Julie a little bit it's
not the easiest thing in the world
because there's a lineage to lineage
thing just as there's a human to human
and human to human thing I couldn't be
more admiring and the lineage to lineage
thing I'm thinking like what am i doing
and so you know the ability to sort of
share be able to share that with you at
a metacognitive level and to also just
like laugh at the whole thing you know
that to modern human beings are talking
about something that we can't even
imagine going through ourselves but can
I say something that what the what am i
doing
question yeah is what we where we need
to get to to open up this new space that
is the purpose of your podcast
well that's the thing was that we've got
to break out of these things I'm very
concerned for them at the moment in our
country in the u.s. that the the
Democratic Party has gone into this kind
of emotional feeling we can't say no to
anybody and you know diversity is is
strength and we should sort of there are
no people who are illegal and why should
somebody born outside the u.s. be any
less fortunate than some so this sort of
christlike stance on all things which i
think is incredibly irresponsible and
very very dangerous because it's not
sustainable and only Christ was Christ
if anybody at all was Christ on the
other hand you see this troglodytic
perspective which is just like you know
I'm tired of feeling guilty and this is
our country and very close to
ethno-nationalism even if it isn't as
the the media portrays it it's certainly
inching in directions that I find
terrifying
I don't know what to do about it because
I just want both of these parties to go
away for very different reasons and I
think that they're feeding off of each
other and our worst instincts and I feel
like the hard work is done when people
sit down with people who are very
different than than them and find out
that the conversations they end up
having don't don't sound anything like
the conversations we might have imagined
hmm yes and who are prepared to be open
to an evolution because humans humans
like everything in little other living
beings beings on this planet develop
move forward in an evolutionary way and
so when you have these parties screaming
out vision visions to me are very
dangerous visions of things of how
things are going to be unbelievably
dangerous and you know all of the most
destructive leaders have had them and
but people who are inching their way
forward in this evolution and having
doing the slow work of repairing the
bonds between us is what is needed and
the other stuff to me is yeah it's it's
it's always it's always going to lead to
a repeat you know just a rerun of the
past you know I've mentioned this before
I was going to start the podcast with
this cousin who I had never met but I've
been talking to a little bit on and off
over the years who lived in Indiana and
she was a mingle a twin who
I had an incredible story in the camps
and I spoke to her just before the
podcast started and before she left on
her and her annual pilgrimage to
Auschwitz and she was really excited
about about it she had freed herself by
having to go to the extraordinary
lengths of forgiving dr. Mengele and the
first time I heard that I had a cousin
who had forgiven dr. Mengele I was so
pissed like how how can you do that you
cannot let this person off the hook you
know that there's responsibility when I
talked to her I realized I hadn't
understood what a genius move this was
so I was like I had to take this anger
that I felt and realize that first of
all she had been through this episode
and me getting angry on behalf of her
was a little rich when she wasn't angry
herself it was one thing if she was
gonna carry that her perspective was I
than her name was Eva I even needed to
free myself from victimhood by doing
what he couldn't what dr. Mengele
couldn't stop me from doing he couldn't
stop me from the grave from forgiving
him when I had every reason not to and
she had no desire to forget or to let
him off the hook but simply did use her
power not to be his victim and this
woman was in it
incredible powerhouse and she was a
next-level thinker and I'm sorry that I
only got a chance to really even connect
with her at the very very end she dies
on this trip to Auschwitz so she can't
make it onto the portal is my first
episode I learned a ton from talking to
her about that which is that we do have
bizarre powers to write off things that
still might have some value to let
people go or to find arrangements in
which we can pass power back and forth
I'm talking more about this on the
podcast the way I see it is that
we Jews have the power to celebrate
German culture there's a lot of things
that happened in Germany that were
unbelievable that happened well before
Adolf Hitler ever came to power and
there are you know if I could just even
talk about things that Nazis did that
are incredibly beautiful and profound so
for example there's a guy named pascal
jordan who contributed some of the
algebra around quantum mechanics that
finds its way into beautiful exceptional
algebraic structures i love his work it
was a straight-up Nazi or I've you know
communicated with karl christian von
weizsäcker the economist who was the son
of I guess a Nazi physicist it's very
clear that this kind of German precision
enters into the work that this economist
was doing one of the few people who
could evaluate some of my work so there
are ways in which we have to be in
dialogue even with our purist
representation of true evil and have to
be able to have a more nuanced
relationship with it lest the childlike
relationship of you know this is pure
bad and can't be talked about no now
it's gonna come erupting out of
Pandora's Box trying to figure out how
to put that to bed by having these more
difficult more nuanced conversations
there's a lot of what what the portal is
supposed to be about I wonder if we
could turn it just towards the end to to
your mom the sadness that I feel in
listening to your story is you know at
one level it's cosmic it's about you
know two important cultures that were
intertwined in some kind of crazy
mimetic rivalry an earlier world war
reparations and the disaster that came
from that
but then there's just this very personal
thing about you and your mom and a
question of how do we Rican SEP schewe
lies the works I don't even think you
had a choice in I think you had to do
this work I think you were compelled and
it was inexorable in some sense one
thing you talked talked to me about was
the idea that in Germany is that in all
cultures there's a concept of
besmirching one's family and you can you
say with the word for this nest bish
matzah which means one who dirties the
nest and I was thinking about this from
the perspective of this restoration work
in art that what you're doing is is that
the nest was B schmutz if you would buy
by the cheap coat of paint over the top
of it and I don't think your goal is to
focus just on the whole I think your
goal is to restore the nest and that
that work may be pretty tough is that a
fair read yes and yes it's my goal I if
I try to conceptualize that restoration
as we're all going to be able to sit
around the table and be loving to each
other and have natural relationships
with one another in my at least with
that with the generation that came
before me as my mother's generation then
I probably won't succeed I'm not going
to try and create that expectation in my
heart a restoration has taken place in
the sense that I have sympathy I don't
hate
I'm not furious and angry at everybody
who came before me I see their different
facades you can't forgive what some of
them did but it's not for me to forgive
so there's nothing to do
about it it's the victims who should
decide whether to forgive or not like
your relative but when it comes to my
own family my children and my husband
who are my family now that is my nest
and it's sharing a nest of course with
with the others too and and that part is
becoming more like the beautiful
painting at the beginning of the series
the complex painting when I first had to
appear on television when the book was
released in Sweden in in January and
Swedish language I was asked to come and
have an interview on morning television
and it was the first time when the story
really hit the headlines everywhere in
Sweden and it was a big deal in Sweden
as it was quite a big deal and suddenly
after I came off this interview I became
very frightened about how my children
would feel because I didn't anticipate
that this would be such a big deal and
suddenly it was and I thought how will
my children feel all their friends will
know everybody he knows them know that
I'm their mother and how do they react
to this because I had not you know
talked to them constantly about this
through the years neither had I hidden
it from them but now we were in a
different situation and well my daughter
fixed it my daughter my daughter showed
me that we will move forward be able to
hold this complexity and she showed me
by calling me up and saying mom I'm
proud of you and it wasn't so much that
the need to feel that my daughter was
proud of me that was so important but
what was important
was that she could feel the emotion of
pride in our family about being open
about what happened and that she doesn't
feel any form of hatred or anger or
anything to any of the characters in the
story rather she can see and she can
behold it and she knows and she can then
draw strength from that and move forward
with that into a society that's changing
very quickly and so if there's anything
that I any restoration work that I hope
I've succeeded in its in in that piece
in in in making the part of the nest
that's inhabited by my children and me
and my husband more true yes I'm yeah
look I can't tell you how well it's not
even you I really want to be talking to
I think it's really like I want to be
talking to your mom and I want to be
letting somebody know that on the other
side of this it's not just a question of
shame and sticking somebody's head in
the toilet bowl for the rest of eternity
forcing them to relive the worst parts
of everything it's a question of it
really needs to be understood that this
happened you know it was as bad as we
say it was and that that is not the
entire story and in particular this
issue of passing power back and forth
when people who have lineage and
connection to the perpetrators of what
happened during this darkest of periods
in human history talk about these things
and own them from the lineage
perspective because you can't own it
personally because it wasn't you and it
allows the rest of us to do the other
part of the work which is to say you
know I've always felt vaguely guilty
about
how attached I am to Schubert leader or
you know music is huge for me so you
know whether it's Bach or Beethoven er
yeah me to record Strauss is my favorite
right there you go and you know I
remember the first time I was in Berlin
and somebody said my Germanic last name
I never wanted to go to Germany because
of my trauma and that suddenly I had
this question did that sound awful or
did it sound awesome you know it's a
very weird thing to be bound up I think
that in part Yiddish which is really
some version of Judaic middle high
german we've gotten divorced from
Yiddish Kight the culture that in part
you know surrounds this language because
of this horrible history so I think that
there's so much to be gained from people
like you you know sort of owning the
connection to it and talking about the
the deepening of understanding of it and
the rest of us who are in a position to
do the other part of that work which
just letting your mom know I couldn't
very easily celebrate things that are
Germanic which have had a huge impact
and a hugely positive impact on the
world without people like your daughter
writing books like this and having the
courage to go on the lecture circuit
talking about the unspeakable and so I
think it's really important that we
figure out how to restore Germany to her
rightful place in the world order as the
last people to have touched the
Holocaust from any side you know take
their take their last spouse the one
thing out let's let's leave on is you
told me something I didn't know about
child rearing in Germany and empathy and
I wonder if you could just share that a
little bit with our listeners and then
I'll say a couple of words and well I
didn't know about it either really
except through observation in my
my own experience until death sight
major German daily newspaper finally
published the research findings that
show that child raising techniques that
were practiced in some of the more
radical Nazi families but this was this
was these were techniques that were
summarized in a book that was written by
somebody called dr. Johanna Hara in 1934
this book was published and it was a
book that made its way into many Nazi
households especially households of ss
families and these were ideas about how
to raise children but not only how to
raise children it was how to raise them
for the struggle because the the
motivating idea behind Hitler's society
was that there was a constant struggle
going on between the races and the the
you know the the Aryans and the other
degenerate people's and and so the the
effect of these practices if if you take
them in their sum total is to remove
empathy from people and there were all
kinds of ways in which this took place
mothers weren't supposed to look into
their infants eyes and things like that
and of course I don't think that most
mothers that implemented these things
were conscious that that's what they
were doing but that was the that was the
effect and I'm not saying that those
babies ended up with no empathy but what
the research is showing is that those
babies that are now elderly people are
moving into in their 70s if I don't know
if you regard a person in their 70s as
elderly but anyway there
I used to but I'm not yeah that's why I
added that but but what is emerging is
that in families where these techniques
were implemented in a systematic manner
the effects on the children were very
serious and this there was research
available about this already back in the
early 90s but no German paper wanted to
touch it no one wanted to publish it
long and it was at the beginning of this
year
dete site at the courage to publish an
article about this which was almost
immediately translated into english and
published in Scientific American and
without going into the details when I
read about it I recognized a lot of
things and just emotionally from from
from things reactions the behavior as
I'd seen and the generation that came
before me
the behavior between my grandmother and
her children things that I then
experienced because no one in my family
really confronted you have to confront
what came before you in order not to
repeat it and unfortunately that didn't
happen so I am familiar with some of
these things and I think this is going
to be very a very big thing and very
important for a lot of families that
this is coming up out into the open now
I think it's also important because
there are other places where extremism
exists in the world and questions about
whether the children of extremists
should be it should remain with those
extremists or not right and I must say
with my with with what I know I would
question whether that's a good idea in
all cases because maybe some of those
children would be better off being
raised in other families depends on a
number of things and child of extremists
I know I don't know what to say about
that but but I I think what I can can
say is that the tendrils of that time
are so long and so many yeah that the
remembering yeah will go on in another
way and it's going to go on for a very
long time and it is the remembering will
happen through those kinds of things
these child-rearing practices or
something that have left an imprint on
families through generations
what is more shocking is that in 1945
when the war was over right and this
this particular book which was called
the German mother and her first child
should have been put on a big heap and
well maybe we should burn books but it
should have just been it no I want to
read it and instead the worst Nazi
ideology was taken out of it it was
republished and also translated to a
number of European languages and sold
continued to be sold throughout Europe
so these ideas continued to affect you
know people into the 1960s and then 70s
there was a break with this you know
late 60s there were the student revolts
in Germany and then there was a sort of
and and also student revolts in
different parts of Europe and so it was
you yeah exactly and so then this stuff
started to be people distanced
themselves from this but it continued to
have an impact after the war so there
are these continuities that means that
the tendrils of the Nazis reached even
further that's not to say that the
techniques that were in there are solely
attributable to the Nazis because they
also drew on thinking that came before
then this is you know there's an
intertwining
you have responsible and even very high
german thought with this very dangerous
and lone
theism authoritarian and
authoritarianism and of course you know
it's not like there's no country on
earth that's been immunized from the
authoritarian tendencies and you know
there are founding murders and
atrocities found everywhere I don't want
to overdo the idea that this is totally
singular to Germany but just with this
empathy riff maybe we could close it out
by me asking for something that I would
never be able to ask for if you hadn't
done the hard work and might show a
payoff to your family and and anyone
else who's interested I would never want
to hear a humanizing story about your
life with your great with with your
grandmother and not a Germanic one but
because of this work I wonder if we
shouldn't sort of explore a payoff of it
which is can you take me into something
that's really precious and sweet to you
about your relationship with your
grandma as you said it committed not see
till 103 or whatever it is the this work
opens up to show what the benefit is of
actually confronting this that this is
something that would be of interest to
somebody who would would never be of
interest to me and after it native their
circumstance when I was writing the last
chapter of my book and actually it was
that was the short version of the book
so that's no longer the last chapter but
now it's somewhere in the middle of the
book but it is the part of of the
pendulum where I reflect on my
grandmother's death because she passed
away in 2014 somewhere in the middle of
where I was doing my research and when I
first excuse me when I first wrote this
section about my reflection on her
passing I hurled my fury at her and then
I took those pages and I sat in the
couch and I thought that's a lie that's
a lie you're just doing that for
everybody else
because everybody else wants you to hate
her yeah but you don't hate her you
don't you love her but you also realize
that she did she supported very bad
things yep
and so I wrote rewrote it and what I
wrote there was a recognition that my
grandmother had influenced me and formed
my life in ways that I can never
quantify she was an enormous influence
on my life yeah yes she was and well
partly led me into this research after
all it was her willingness to speak with
me over very very many years about many
things just not just not certain pieces
of that the essential truth was just
that they were an SS couple but she was
willing to speak with me about very many
things opened up for me the gray zone
that women inhabited under Nazism that
they were both victims and perpetrators
at the same time because Nazism also
promoted male violence including at home
and so I'm very formed by her and I
recognized it there and I went back to
one particular memory which is which is
a sweet memory of her that I try to keep
in my mind I don't cling to it because I
can actually today hold both the memory
of her sitting there in a harsh voice
trying to convince me the Holocaust
didn't happen as well as this sweet
memory but you can't let one memory
erase the other one because then you're
not you're not dealing with the reality
you're not facing the truth so the other
memory is
when I was a young girl and I was I was
kind of chubby as some young girls are
and my mother sent me to stay with her
rather than in the apartment where the
rest of the family were staying because
my grandmother was into health food into
healthy food and she had a way of
handling food in a very sparing way as
many people from a ward or generation
people person has been through two world
wars is very sparing with food and she
would prepare a muesli for the following
day the night before because it had to
it had to rest before you ate it on the
next morning it was a way of handling
the fruits of the earth with respect in
a way that we don't do in our consumer
society that's a problem and we sat
there grading an apple together and I
would watch her grading this Apple with
such reverence into this bowl because
she really appreciated every ingredient
and she would talk quietly to me in her
tiny little kitchen about you know not
having food the absence of food why this
Apple was healthy and the next day the
next morning we would eat it together
together in this apartment and to me is
a positive memory it's a simple memory
it's full of it's full of things that we
have lost in our society that perhaps we
need to find our way back to greater
reverence for things that the earth
produces and so I keep that with me next
to the other memories as well well thank
you for trusting me with and my audience
with a beautiful vignette from your life
with your grandma and for making it
possible just to understand the
complexity you know the old adage that
hurt
will hurt people there were a lot of
hurt people in Germany before the Nazis
came to power and people got swept up in
things and there's responsibility and a
lack of responsibility and I assume
we'll spend like many years trying to
sort out what's what but I want to just
say thank you at it like the most human
of levels I have so much love for you
and your project what you're trying to
do Julie so thanks for coming on the
program and sharing your story with us
thank you Eric for doing the hard work
no no it's you who's doing the hard work
the book people is the pendulum check it
out the author is julie Linda you've
been listening to us discuss this
important work and this important book
so thanks for coming through the portal
with Julie and please remember to
subscribe to the podcast wherever you
listen to podcast be that stitchers
modify Apple or if you listen on YouTube
make sure to subscribe and click the
bell so you'll be but no one ever we
drop our next episode
[Music]